A ball is kicked with an initial speed of
metres per second and an angle of 40
degrees
above the horizontal. So, first of all,
let
me note that its initial speed is 20
metres
per second and an angle of 40 degrees to
the
horizontal. And we want to know what the
total
distance or displacement it has when it
finally
lands. And we can assume a lot of things,
which
is very common in kinematics questions.
So, assume no air resistance and we are on
a
flat plane. So, to help you out with this,
let
me first draw a diagram. So, here it is
and
here's the ball on the ground. It is
kicked
with an initial speed of 20 metres
per second and an angle of 40 degrees.
So, now what we want to do is we want to
split
this question into two parts.
The first part is, well, we first know
that
the ball's trajectory is going to go
something
like this. The first part is to see and
break
down our 20 metres per second vector into
components,
like we have learned in the previous part.
We break it down into components. So,
right
here, let me just do that, 20 metres per
second,
40 degrees. So, I want you guys to tell me
what
the x component and what the y component
is
of this vector. Pause the video and resume
when
you're done. So, for the x component, if
we
imagine it like a triangle like we always
do,
we get 20 times cose of 40 degrees.
20 times cose of 40 is around 15.32,
but I would store the full number
somewhere
on your calculator because this is not
your
final answer. So, you want your numbers to
be
exact as possible. Next up is the v of y.
So, v of x is this. v of y is 20 times
sine
of 40 degrees, which is around 12.86
metres per second.
Oops, did not mean to do that.
metres per second and 12.86 metres per
second.
So, what this means is that the ball is
going
12.86 metres per second to the right and
15.32
metres per second to vertically,
initially.
Now, you're going to be thinking, well,
how
will we calculate it? Well, think to
yourself,
when does the ball actually stop?
When does it land? Well, it lands when the
y
becomes zero again. When you look at these
three
equations, what do you have?
And we can use what we have to see which
equation
we want to use. First of all, we got to
find
the time, and the time depends on the y
component
because the ball lands when the y
is zero. It doesn't matter if the x
component,
it travelled 10 metres or 100 metres, the
ball
always lands when the y is at zero.
It does not matter about x. So, let's see,
what
do we know about y? Well, we know that the
ball
starts at y equals zero, so y0 is zero.
The ball also ends at y final is zero.
The ball's acceleration in terms of y
is negative 9.81 because it's gravity.
The only thing that's pulling the ball
down
or accelerating the ball is gravity.
And don't forget the negative sign because
we're
assuming that upwards is positive. So,
since
acceleration is a vector, you have to
include
the negative. And we need to find the
time. So, if we have all these values,
if we look in our formula sheet, we could
easily
spot out this formula. And let me
just quickly copy paste this and
move it here. Alright,
now when we use this formula, we can just
plug
in our values. It doesn't matter if it's
x,
y can be used as well, or in 3D cases, z.
So, we know y final is zero.
The initial y is also zero.
And now this is just a matter of plugging
in
numbers. Oh, by the way, vx0, which is the
initial
y velocity, is over here we have this.
We calculated this by splitting the
vector.
And we have 12.86 plus 12.86t
plus 1 over 2 times negative 9.81t
squared. And when you actually simplify
it,
1 over 2 times negative 9.81 is about
negative
4.905t squared.
You figure out that you get a quadratic.
Well, you might be thinking, well, a
quadratic
has two solutions. How can this be?
Well, this formula is calculating when the
ball is at rest, or is at y equals zero.
And do you know when the ball is at y
equals
zero? Yeah, there's two cases. At the
initial,
when the ball has just been kicked, or
time
equals zero, and at the final, which is
the
time we want to calculate. And we see that
t
equals zero is one of our solutions. When
you
factor out t, you
get t equals zero for one of the
solutions.
The other solution is negative 12.86
equals
negative 4.905t.
And when you do the math, you will get
around
2.62 seconds.
So it takes the ball 2.62 seconds to
complete
its curve, or path, because in 2.62
seconds,
it will be landed. It will land over here.
So now we know that all we do is just
calculate
how far the x component will go in 2.62
seconds,
because ultimately, we're just finding out
how
far this went in terms of x.
And x here is just equal to time times
speed, so v times t.
And when you do v times t, you know t,
2.62,
and velocity would be equal to 12.86.
Sorry, 15.32 metres per second.
And seconds cross out, so we get 2.62
times
15.32, and you get around 40.17
metres. And keep in mind, I used the
horizontal
velocity because we want to calculate the
distance. The vertical velocity is
independent,
and I can't stress that enough.
So that's an example of using 2D
kinematics.
And if you have any questions, you can
always
email me, or meet me after school in
Physics
Club every week, every two weeks.
So thank you, and I hope you learned
something
from this kinematics intro.